Guide to the Benjamin Lee Whorf Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings on Linguistics, 1924-1971; Series II; 4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  - Writings by Others (NOT INCLUDED IN MICROFILM)
    - Nykl, A. R., "Notes on the Spanish of Yucatan, Vera Cruz, and Tlaxcala," Modern Philology, 1930 May (Box 13, Folder 120)
    - Peñafiel, Antonio, Catálogo Alfabético de los Nombres de Lugar Pertenecientes al Idioma "Nahuatl", 1885 (Box 13, Folder 121)
    - Rojas, Mariano J., Manual de la Lengua Nahuatl, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 122)
    - Teeple, John E., Maya Astronomy, 1930 August (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - Teeple, John E., "Maya Inscriptions: Further Notes on the Supplementary Series," American Anthropologist, 1925 October-December (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Tozzer, Alfred M., A Maya Grammar, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - "Codice Maya de Dresden," Anales de la Geografia e Historia, Guatemala, 1930-1931 (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - "Codice de Madrid," Anales de la Sociedad de Geografia e Historia, Guatemala, 1931-1933 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - Clippings, 1931, 1935, undated (Box 13, Folder 128)
- Writings on Science and Religion, 1925-1941, 1955; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  There is no overall organization except that writings on fire insurance are at the end of the series.
  The target at the beginning of Reel 5 mistakenly identifies the material following as being from Series III. Material on frames 1-866 is actually from Series II, WRITINGS ON LINGUISTICS, Research Notes. Series III, WRITINGS ON SCIENCE AND RELIGION, begins, instead, at frame 867. The target at frame 867 incorrectly identifies the material following as being from Series IV.
  - "Why I Have Discarded Evolution": typescript, correspondence, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 1, Reel 5U)
  - ["Concerning Science and Religion"]: manuscript, [1925?] (Box 14, Folder 2, Reel 5U)
  - "Library books read beginning Jan. 1925": list, 1925-1928 (Box 14, Folder 3, Reel 5U)
  - Drawings related to philosophic and scientific writings, 1934, 1936, undated (Box 14, Folder 4, Reel 5U)
  - "Part I: The Flux-Outlet Theory," "Part II: The Expansion Theory": manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 5, Reel 5U)
  - "In Defense of Puritanism": manuscript, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 6, Reel 5U)
  - "Largest-Stemmed Plants": manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 7, Reel 5U)
  - "Pines": manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 7, Reel 5U)
  - Untitled manuscript notes on Mexican trees and shrubs, 1936 December 19 (Box 14, Folder 7, Reel 5U)
  - "Light-Velocity and Expansion": manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 8, Reel 5U)
  - "On Being": transcript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - "Universal Trinity in Unity": outline, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - "A Fragment from the Song of Creation": typescript (translation?), undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - Letter in response to a critic of Darwinian theory: manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - Letter in English writer comparing civilizations: manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - Essay on consciousness and perception: manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - Index, undated (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel 5U)
  - "Unanswered Question from Ancient Times": typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 10, Reel 5U)
  - ["A Trip to Southern Florida"]: manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 11, Reel 5U)
  - Notebook on botany, undated (Box 14, Folder 11, Reel 5U)
  - Writings about fire insurance
    - "Blazing Icicles": reprints, correspondence, 1941, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 12, Reel 5U)
    - "The Flying Kettle": manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 13, Reel 5U)
    - "A Suggested Classification of Insurance": mimeograph, undated (Box 14, Folder 14, Reel 5U)
    - Other manuscripts, typescripts (Box 14, Folder 15, Reel 5U)
- Biographical Material, 1914-1957; Series IV; 0.25; (1 box)
  Articles about Whorf and photographs of him precede printed material collected by him.
  The target at frame 867 of reel 5 incorrectly identifies the material following as being from Series IV. In fact, BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, Series IV, begins at frame 1363. The target at frame 1363 correctly identifies this material.
  "Photographs of Benjamin Lee Whorf and Ernest Naquayouma, 1914-1918?, undated" (formerly in Box 15, folder 3) are missing from the collection as of 1980. Both are pictured in the newspaper clippings in box 15, folder 2.
  - Articles about Whorf, 1933-1957, n.d (Box 15, Folder 1, Reel 5U)
  - Newsclippings about Whorf, 1931-1937 (Box 15, Folder 2, Reel 5U)
  - Obituaries, 1949 July (Box 15, Folder 4, Reel 5U)
    General note
    See also: Series I, 1953 Mar 29 and Apr 8; 1954 Feb 3; box 2, folder 28.
  - Printed matter, 1923-1931, n.d (Box 15, Folder 5, Reel 5U)
  - Programs and circulars
    - The American Anthropological Association, 1928-1939 (Box 15, Folder 6, Reel 5U)
    - Linguistic Society of America, 1928-1940 (Box 15, Folder 7, Reel 5U)
- Lantern Slides, undated; Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  There is no inventory of the slides, but some have descriptive labels.
  LANTERN SLIDES has not been included in the microfilm.
  - Lantern Slides, undated (Box 16–19)
- Additional Material, 1898-1945; Accession 2006-M-081
  This accession to the Benjamin Lee Whorf Papers is arranged alphabetically by category. Within categories, correspondence and diaries, the bulk of the materials, are arranged chronologically; subject files and writings alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    - Family, 1928, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters of introduction, 1929 December 20, 1930 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Professional/personal, 1928, 1940-1942, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1915-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 10)
  - Diaries, 1932-1941 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 15)
  - Diaries, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 16 - 18)
  - News clippings, 1928-1932, 1937, 1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Subject files
    - General Semantics, Second American Conference on, [preliminary outline and notes], 1941 August 1, 2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1918, 1928, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Mayan decoration, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Piano music [handwritten scores composed by Benjamin Lee Whorf], 1916-1918, 1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 23 - 25)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Writings
    - Essays
      - "Decipherment of the Linguistic Portion of the Maya Hieroglyphs", Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Untitled, Undated (Box 3)
    - Poetry
      - "The Hypnotic Burglar", [1908] (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - "Night in the Woods", 1913, undated (Box 3)
      - Notebook with poems and sketches, [1918] (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Benjamin Lee Whorf, [1898, 1899, undated] (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Additional Material, Circa 1925-1941; Accession 2011-M-076
  - The Ruler of the Universe
    - Manuscript, Chapter IV, "Certain Things Considered", Circa 1925-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, Circa 1925-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)